# HILLEL STEINMETZ

### ABOUT ME:

I am a University of Chicago graduate with one year of research experience in behavioral science research. Previously, I worked for the University of Chicago's Department of Psychology, where I was involved in research on the effects of non-literal language on social cognition, the psychology of civic virtues, and speech perception.

My research interests are in the sociology and social psychology of identity. I am particularly fascinated by the relationship between partisan and religious identity. I am also interested in sociolinguistics and Jewish intellectual history.

### **EDUCATION:**

The University of Chicago, Chicago, IL

Bachelor of Arts in Linguistics, June 2019

Cumulative GPA: 3.92/4.00 o Major GPA: 4.00/4.00

**Honors and Grants**: Leonard Bloomfield Prize in Linguistics (June 2019), *Phi Beta Kappa* (May 2018), PRISM Research Grant (June 2018)

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE:

#### June 2019 - Research Assistant

Aug. 2020

Attention, Perception, and Experience Lab | University of Chicago | Chicago, IL

- Worked with Professor Anne Henly to study the role of metaphor in perspective-taking and social closeness and assisted with a project researching how to cultivate civic virtue in a classroom setting
- Analyzed and summarized large data sets using Excel, R, and SPSS
- Helped facilitate lab operations, such as teaching graduate students to use software and resolving technical issues

#### June 2019 - Research Assistant

June 2020

Goldin-Meadow Lab | University of Chicago | Chicago, IL

- Worked with Jenny Lu to research how speech rate, a paralinguistic cue, can be
  used to convey semantic information—specifically, how non-native vs. native
  speakers process these cues
- Conducted study on 50+ participants online and in-person and analyzed data in R

### June 2018 - Undergraduate Research Assistant

**June 2019** 

Attention, Perception, and Experience Lab | University of Chicago | Chicago, IL

- Generated descriptive summaries of text transcription and presented these findings at a symposium and lab meetings
- Created an online experiment (Inquisit) researching the social effects of metaphor

# Feb. 2018 - Undergraduate Research Assistant

Iune 2019

Goldin-Meadow Lab | University of Chicago | Chicago, IL

- Helped create an in-person experiment on speech rate processing (E-Prime)
- Collected and modified 120+ image and sound stimuli using Praat and image editing software

# Nov. 2016 Sapir Scholar Undergraduate Research Assistant

- June 2017

Phonology Lab | University of Chicago | Chicago, IL

- Conducted research with Jacob Phillips investigating the sociolinguistics of an ongoing sound change in English sibilants "s" and "sh" that related to listener judgments of gender and sexuality
- Recruited speakers of Chicago English and synthesized a phonetic spectrum of sibilants that varied in acoustic frequency in Praat

# Posters, Presentations, and Papers:

[Paper] Hillel Steinmetz, "Rabbinic Conceptions of Torah In Avot And Its Role in The Establishment of a New Religious Society." *Makom: The University of Chicago's Undergraduate Journal of Jewish Thought,* June 2019.

[Presentation] Hillel Steinmetz and Anne Henly, "The Effects of Metaphor on Perspective Taking, Communication, and Intimacy." University of Chicago PRISM Symposium, November 2018.

[Poster] Jacob Phillips and Hillel Steinmetz, "Phonological environment conditions social perception of sibilants." Invited to present at NWAV 46 at the University of Wisconsin-Madison, November 2017.

# **A**CADEMIC **S**ERVICE:

Editor-In-Chief, *Makom*: the University of Chicago's Undergraduate Journal of Jewish Thought Chicago, IL, August 2018 – June 2019

### **ACTIVITIES AND LEADERSHIP:**

Advisory Board Member, Hillel at the University of Chicago Chicago, IL, September 2017 – June 2019

Associate Editor (formerly Staff Writer and Contributor), The *Chicago Maroon* Chicago, IL, October 2015 — March 2017

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS:**

R, SPSS, Excel, Qualtrics, LaTeX, Inquisit, Praat, Python (basic), C (basic)

## Languages:

Modern Hebrew (fluent), Classical Hebrew (intermediate), French (working proficiency)